okay so I had in mind to speak about a
noble friendship like what the Buddha
says about that and how to cultivate
that so I'll start with that kind of the
most famous to death about noble
friendship it's in the song eating
nakiya let's see um king pasenadi is
visiting them but he says here venerable
sir while I was alone in seclusion the
following reflection arose in my mind
dum has been well expounded by the
Blessed One it is for one it is for one
with good friends good companions good
comrades not for one with bad friends
bad companions and bad comrades so it is
great kings so it is this demo has been
well expanded by me and it is for the
good one with good friends never win bad
friends I'm on occasion great king I was
living among the seconds where there's a
town named Naraku Vigo and lambda
approached me paid homage to me and sat
down to one side it said venerable sir
this is half the holy life that is good
friendship good companionship could come
wretched when this was said I told the
become Ananda not so on them not so this
is the entire holy life Ananda that is
good friendship whose companionship good
comradeship when a Baku has a good
friend a good companion a good comrade
is to be expected that he will develop
and cultivate the Noble Eightfold Path
and how does it be Google as a good
friend a good companion a good comrade
develop and cultivate the Noble
Eightfold Path here and under Vickery
develops right view which is based upon
seclusion dispassion and cessation
maturing and release and so on with all
the other factors so here even then he's
there's more to wait for that here even
he's saying like blazes the collectors
are based on seclusion with a good no
that's the other thing I mean I'm sure
you've heard it before but I myself many
many times
heard that's what the quoted but only
part is to the quartet
only the first part but it says and it's
called by monks and nuns as well in the
talks saying how the
Noba friendship is the entirety of the
holy life and then they wouldn't explain
how but instead going talking about how
community company camaraderie in a sense
we're doing things together with
together together together together
he's justifiable by that quote which it
isn't because you carry on reading the
same suit and it would explain how it's
because you take him on as a friend
which means with a friendly eye you
regard what he said could be beneficial
for you and out of that faith in that
friendship you go forth you never even
meet the Buddhist by the way you just
heard about it and you regard him as a
friend and you leave your home become a
monk out of that faith make the effort
get the right view and you verify his
teaching without ever meeting him
there's nothing to do it's sort of
hanging out and in spending time
together it's to do basically with
having friends that know more than you
in terms of the Dhamma and in learning
but exactly it says that it's based on
seclusion what you're going to learn
through friendship is based on seclusion
we draw a sense restraint and all that
so it's it's it's it's a it's a far cry
from from from justifying community
group activities and whatnot almost like
a distinction I think between the
consensual friendship Thursday and this
other kind yeah the thing is people
depend on company more often than not
the solitude is not pleasant so then if
you are already given in to their
dependence and you're ignoring a
responsibility for it you will then just
look for anything remotely to justify it
and the first part of that suta serves
that purpose because you don't need the
other bit pretty good it's almost like
an abstract friendship there the Buddha
talks about I can't have a meet him you
just hear about him and you know it's
it's friendly of friendly disposition
and because of that you go forward but
you don't mention that because that
would that would undermine the purpose
of of trying to justify
you know being able to withstand
seclusion it's almost a sense of like
you're it's like it's like almost like a
intertwine with like faith in that sense
like this hi there this is friend yeah
that's exactly what he said it's out of
that because of that friendship they
they trust either of this trust it or
this this could help me if they don't
regard him with a friendly eye in that
sense he wouldn't you wouldn't you know
you would look for faults you wouldn't
committed in your certain will have
faith in it so basically what he's
saying whoever wants to help you if you
perceive oh this could help me that's
already a form of friendship you can
also not regard him as a friend even if
you don't necessarily know whether it
would be successful or not they promised
to help Sam then like it's almost like
an acknowledgement of her mmm
like fundamental isolation fundamental
sovereigns because it's like this person
the friend because they can help me but
not like that kind of way people
denigrate either yeah yeah there's no
other way around it thank you you will
have to start selfishly mm-hmm there's a
certain type of selfishness can result
in cessation of selfishness and that
type of substance is practicing the
Dharma that type of craving is craving
for the understanding of the Dharma oh
and they type you can see it is a
conceit for you know being another hand
being a being one of the enlightened
beings but because of their conceit
because of their craving because of its
selfishness you actually are making the
effort in the right direction they will
cancel those very things when when when
you do a right list eventually yeah
other times with people who delight in
company it has always seemed to me that
I was denying that fundamental no I
think it's like one of the worst
impediments mind of course provided
sense restraints practice yeah that's a
must but then it's the company careless
chatter just just hanging out that's
it's there's so many suitors
it's all about talks about how to not do
that to avoid it why you should
do it like don't be negligent you know
practice occlusion because until it's
too late so so it's not really I mean he
was he was telling off mm-hmm what I was
telling off to the monks probably a
10-month obviously not other hands but
clearly monks on the path they were just
hanging out together sewing robes
preparing for the Catena you know the
things that are good seemingly he would
sort of blast them like really really
really sort of serious serious telling
off because it's just wasting the timing
company yeah you said like who is it
making noise like I'm just fishermen
yeah yeah that's it I'm approaching this
monastery and I thought there's like a
band of fishermen here selling fish and
shouting and it's it's the it's the
monks supposedly practicing and again
when we then you read the citta later
this no they they were crazy do we know
they were actually sewing robes for the
Cuttino occasion and it would have told
them off because yeah but what's the
purpose of your whole life and it
doesn't mean like every getting together
to justify like hating on groups or
something like that no that's your own
personal issue because sometimes people
don't know how to deal with people and
they try to use solitude to justify see
the Buddha say we should be in solitude
yeah for practice not because you hate
everybody else and you can't live with
them because then you're just in
solitude with your own hate so you need
to discern really motivations rooted as
always and once you do then you will do
the solitude rightly so then how will
let's say with that example the person
just hates everyone it's not dead no I'm
gonna not everyone by going to be in
company all the time I will narrate how
are they like address that well you you
address that issue first by as I said by
being aware of the motivation behind
whether your solitude over your company
and again say more often than not people
who try to justify the company the
community the group these people who
don't know how to live alone too afraid
who will eventually start to feel like
you too anxious to without any purpose
without any worldly goal
or project it would be too hard to
handle so then you justified all these
great occasions of monks coming together
and then just basically hang out and
chitchat and ceremonies and whatnot so
you have that side of things but then
yeah you have many people who just have
no social or have little social skills
so they cannot bear other people very
well I don't know how to relate to it
and always results in fiction so then
they go to solitude and coat the suit is
about solitude but where is that routed
is it in this their understanding of
necessity of solitude is a basis for the
practice no it's rooted in the real wealth of
no it's rooted in the real wealth of
those people they don't know how to deal
with so then you won't be doing it for
the right reasons you need to find you
need to reroute your motivation into the
right reasons so there is no like oh you
should then stay with people or you
should then go to solitude
it depends why you do it and if you do
it rightly you will then go to solitude
because it is a necessary basis for a
full night understand whether you're in
like a place like this where there are
people living together so to speak or so
I suppose yeah practical advice would be
if if you are considering finding a
place where you can kind of try a bit of
both that's what you need to look for the
that's what you need to look for the
place that would then allow you if
possible to be in solitude but and also
have some reference point of other
people so you make sure you don't give
in just in whatever you are doing these
rooted in the wrong reasons yeah it's it
seemed variable seems I got me to like
be able to kind of put yourself have
yourself exposed at different situations
good well I think that's the whole idea
of Messiah in the beginning but
obviously having somebody to learn from
it means you're not completely on your
own until until you can be completely on
your own but again people who already
decided that they don't want the
solitude then they would use this to
justify the company in the group when
the Buddha said you need to be prepared
for like you know living
the wilderness dwellings you need to
have the right view established in
virtue sense restrained all these things
and then they will say ok so see so you
must be ready for the solitude ok so is
the company making you ready for the
solitude how's that possible hanging out the
how's that possible hanging out the
people is made preparing me to be alone
how does that work he doesn't so it's a
completely separate decision that you
make ok I'm not ready for the solitude but
ok I'm not ready for the solitude but
that doesn't mean I'm justified for
company no just means I'm not ready for
solitude so make yourself ready for
solitude so wisely use your company and
learning from it so the rest of that
suit days as as you mentioned by
following the following method - and it
may be understood how the entire holy
life is good friendship by relying on me
as a good friend on the being subjective
Bertha free from birth beings of it
aiding her free from aging submit the
illness are freed from illness subject
to death are free from death sorrow
lamentation pain grief and despair are
free from those things is by this by
this method and under it may be
understood how the entire holy life is
good friendship and then he goes on to
say further further exhortation
therefore a great king you should train
yourself thus I would be one respite
friends the comrades good friendship and
when you have good friends you should go
out with one thing for support diligence
and wholesome States
he goes on to say that you should also
exert your all your people do the same
and they're all gonna that'll have be
for your mutual benefit in welfare oh
yeah so basically the good friend is
defined by the one they will whose
presence interaction with will result in
your wisdom increasing it's not defined
by the one that makes me feel good what
makes me so happy makes me feel
and could even be someone who does not
make you feel very happy more often but
I think that's exactly yeah I think
someone who's poking you in the ways you
don't want to be poor but you are not
acting from the point of view of your
precious feelings you're acting out of
recognition what's good feeling and
that's the rhinoceros boy I mean it said
unless you find a friend better or at
least equal he's no friend of yours that
so you should leave you should not hang
with us feel inferior to you and it
refers to the point of view of
understanding and virtue and development
of development of wisdom so so that said
that's important to keep in mind other
words yeah you'll just be oh you know
he's a good mate I like his company
hanging out whatever else so he's a good
friend see there's another suitor that
goes into executives from in good your
book of eights suited to decode John and
I'll just read the part that goes under
good friendship hmm and the butter and
tells this guy what is good friendship
this is for householder but I think it
applies to anyone there is a case where
a householder spends time with
householders or their sons young or old
accomplished in virtue he speaks with
them engages them in discussion
discussion he emulates that
accomplishment in virtue and like why
the faith generosity and wisdom so that
guy's easy staying there it's like the
whole point just to like kind of pick up
the signs almost of like what does it
mean to be like this and then you can
see them which means you already need to
be internally valuing virtue for
yourself otherwise you wouldn't pursue
these people you wouldn't see that as
variable and exactly then you wouldn't
have a discernment for the pursuit but
you won't so you recognize that virtue
is worth being developed and you know
you might try partially successful maybe
not not as much as you will want to so how
not as much as you will want to so how
can I improve this oh let me find those
who are more virtuous than me and let me
learn that from them and let me write it
and then obvious where choices they are
so you benefited from that type of
friendship it's just friendship in order
to do the work not friendship in order
to make yourself feel good in the last
six I had an interesting example of like
this is a kind of like the example of a
quote unquote perfect community
it's from my doing the kaya 31 the Mago
single suit anuradha is living with two
other monks and but is asking how
they're doing and they each say this is
a game for me that I am living with such
companions in the holy life and
maintained bodily verbal and mental acts
of kindness both openly and privately I
consider why should I not set aside what
I wish to do and do what these are the
ones we should to do we are different
and body but one in mind so what do you
make or that last thing why should I not
set aside what I wish to do do it these
venerable wish to do well we could you
realized it or the monk there realizes
that all three of them are pretty much
highly developed so it doesn't matter
whether my point of view thinks this or
his point of view things that being on
the same level so it doesn't matter who
does what as in the future is to do what
he wants because I could have wanted the
same thing because we are on the same
level so in that sense we are just one
in the mind not one in the mind because
again they feel these deep spiritual
connection it's one in the mind because
they share the same level of wisdom
which means the investor the same amount
of effort done the same amount of work
and got the same amount of results and
they recognize that and that's why is
such a blessing as well and easier
binding so even if they don't even speak
they understand where they are again not
know no mystical intuition or I don't
know that it's simply they understood
each other's extends right they don't
have those problems that come with this
kind of imbalances no no space yeah so
so
in externally you cannot necessarily
tell apart but internally having
understood each other there know exactly
where they are at and that's why yes it
doesn't matter I want to do this he
wants to do that doesn't matter it's
coming from the same level of the same
mind there are yes many Samadhi
attainment and such yeah and you see
like the communal getting together was
only been there there was a purpose for
it
preparing for the meal or cleaning after
the meal or were waiting for Penda path
to distribute the food and so on it was
like hey let's get together just for the
sake of company it goes on to say that
like they're saying like there's
actually two examples one occurs here
the other I'll mention after basically
something alone lies like whoever if
you'd see a vessel for drinking water or
vessel for washing water or for rinsing
void and empty should set out water if
it's impossible for him to do this he
should set out water by signaling with
his hand having invited a companion to
help him by movement of his hand
so usually not for that reason break up
into speech the same thing for various
kinds of duties that would they would
have to do it there though please yes
see that's what I mean lookit oh I can't
do solid
thus company is justified once company
is justified getting together for also
two reasons becomes justified once
company justified getting together for
so Theresa justified speaking is
justified actually it isn't it's all
completely different things different
decisions you make on top of each other
it's more like you should you should
look at it the opposite way no I'm
already for the solitude but I must be
ready for the solitude until I'm ready
sorry for the solitude sometimes we have
to come together but at least when we
come together at least let does not
speak if we have to come together and if
we have to speak but at least speak only
with the purpose of something practical
needs to be said or Dhamma discussed so
instead of just justifying it further
you still want to like make it harder
and harder to drift away from the
original purpose of being alone and not
speaking in order to understand
dumb it's similar like with the Buddha
instructed early on his deathbed when
when I was in a hostel with regard to
women and he said don't look at him
well if you have to look at him well
then don't talk to them but if you have
to look at him and talk to them
well then be mindful of the you know why
you became a monk and insensitive
strange and everything else but it's
again as I said it's okay so I have to
do this that's everything else that
could come out of it is also justifiable
so we have to come together so we might
as well just talking address other
things and end up finding new reasons
for coming up together and know so if
you are not ready for the solitude
doesn't mean you're justified in company
the altar well in the end like but every
five days we are those three monks sit
together all night discussing Dhamma hmm
the alternative versions in Davinia it
has the exact same thing except their
their purpose is just never talk to each
other and the better chastises them as
being like goats basically living not
actually content and happy it's almost
like think you think I got people like I
don't like to live with people they hate
just fine avoiding them and yeah we're
getting along yeah so it does seem like
yeah like it's almost it seems almost
like like yeah if you're gonna live in
company you should use the company for
like actual benefit of things not
squander it in that sense exactly and it
doesn't and that is you can also then
conclude from the same point it doesn't
mean any company like you know even mugs
they can be vastly different coming from
last different backgrounds we devised
the different views on what the practice
is and some of it is more compatible
something and not all they want to learn
equally so that doesn't mean you can
just all because you were rope and as I
said if the occasion comes you know
there is a whole educate the whole
seniority which is that's exactly the
purpose of that so there is no friction
nothing you just do it professionally
follow along but we are talking about
actually living with somebody in some
proximity getting together doing things
so you realize it requires wisdom and
discern internally for your own sake to be able
internally for your own sake to be able
to pass to be able to discern this
rightly externally so it's not just off
wherever you bundle with just you know
make it work right sure it doesn't work
like that because you shouldn't be
bundled with anyone to begin with so
then if you do have to be bundle with
somebody because you're not ready for a
sari together you don't have the right
view you're not your own guide as the
suit to say well then bundle is somebody
they will enable you that not like all
this you know I get on with him but he's
equally ignorant is iron and we just
randomly step in the dark thinking maybe
one of us would stumble upon the dump
so yeah in that sense fundamentally like
when it says you know the word kalyana
admit that I think he said it's not
before us it's always going to be an
aureus Africa so you know like no like
even that I mean if you have done a very
wholesome bit toward you knows better
than animals exactly that's the the
other so they call it at all to learn
the virtue in generosity including it
but don't confuse virgin generosity for
the practice of Dhamma that's a whole
new level now so that's the thing
you recognize you know ready for
seclusion find a friend they will make
you ready for seclusion and so how how
should one then we've mentioned this is
a mystery forever like you know one can
be in seclusion amidst company my
calendar says like a practicing monk
even when people visit in all kinds of
important people his mind inclines still
towards the seclusion well you won't
arrive at that through company that's I
mean the key of mine still has to be as
the Buddha said in climbing to its
seclusion and renunciation and you can
only develop the mind in climbing in the
direction by doing it so then once
you've been doing it once that becomes
your mode of being that seclusion then
yet people Kings turning up he's not a
disturbance because the mind is still in
that seclusion but you will not arrive
at that by never actually doing it by
staying the company and then justifying
your kind of need of company through
saying see I can become independent
it's like similar somebody who is not
restrained from sensuality he's
justifying their non restraint of
sensuality and begins to practice the
Dhamma and then the result of the Dhamma
will somehow restrain them of sensuality
no results of the Dhamma results of
restraint of sensuality not all the way
around so this is the same your mind
will enjoy the seclusion as a result of
you practicing the seclusion and then
yes even the company will not disturb it
so theoretically everybody is able to
develop that but you cannot do it on the
basis of the lifestyle that contradicts
it like it just becomes Union normal in
that sense yeah it becomes well it
becomes an excuse you know now we'll see
the Buddha said you can be alone in the
company thus I shouldn't I don't have to
leave my company you can be alone in the
company through being alone first
otherwise he wouldn't say the virtue and
sense restraint and seclusion comes
first but he didn't say that many of
times even in the actual the first suit
I recorded on calamita he said so how
did what is this venture we are
assaulting them understanding and
practicing seclusion and getting the
right deal as a result of their
friendship there was one story that
interested me like in the parinibbana
citta it said like we know in the
windows passing away or he already
passed away
I don't remember Ananda he was only a
sotapanna at the time isn't that for
many many years but even then like he
broke down and you know said that kind
of stands oh it says like my mind that
Law Society Bhutto died oh he was a very
sunny Buddha died he said off my mind
he's like yeah because brothers the tree
that I'm jealous and drown it yeah so
like in that sense it sounded like yike
maybe he hadn't fully been clarified
like his relationship towards sorry oh
yes they're not no because because in
the same so they said those monks who
were on a hunts they were not grieving
they said how can that which has a
reason not cease it was just an absolute
matter of fact that people will die and
you could like having feelings about it
is inconceivable once you fully
understood that to the fact that he had
feelings means he hasn't fully understood exactly
means he hasn't fully understood exactly
that company in the relationship with
did you to have anything to bring that
for mention I was most of what I had to
bring the only thing I would think of
course that job like often Mehta is
transferred as loving-kindness but then
it's friendship friendliness yes yeah
yes the same yeah means not hard and
you're unable to have your will doesn't
mean smarmy wishful thinking yeah it
could very well mean leaving someone
alone that's your most friendly thing to
do yeah but you know when the when the
Buddha talks about compassion and so on
it seals many times she describes what
kind of compassion it is it's a
compassion of a doctor they can help you
it's a compassion of a of a parent that
sticks his hand into the throat of his
child to pull the thing he's choking on
so he'll rip his throat up and you make
it bleed but you'll say this what
anybody said it isn't whom he does so so
that's what I mean like you need to
start using the criteria both friendship
instruction not based on how it makes
you feel but after like heavily invested
effort in discerning is this beneficial
in a long run which is better for me
being pleased now with inspirational
verses from some spiritual poet or being
told you know the truth it might
slightly offend me but deep down I know
already yeah it makes more sense so in other
yeah it makes more sense so in other
words you will not have a spiritual
friend carvanha maintain the correct sense
carvanha maintain the correct sense
unless you start developing wisdom for
yourself because you can complete idea
for what a true friend is you might have
met them and you got offended by it and
then the ones that make you feel good
and tell you what you want to hear well
they're not your friends there's a funny
City the one about like
some guy does the butter the butter
tells him like you know suffering is
born from those who are dear but he
doesn't like and so he goes to some
gamblers no these are my friends I like
they agreed with him yeah yeah exactly
yeah they just went to verify one you
know two people to tell you but he wants
to hear
cuz he had my own practice a lot of
times it's been like you know kind of
hearing that you've been overlooking
something it hurts but it's like wow if
I hadn't like been like poked in that
way like it's almost like a relief in
the back of your mind but there's an
opportunity to be like rejected by the
other your mind wants to do ya know like
yeah you don't even realize how lucky
you are did your going to figure out
yourself oh yeah I don't want to
hear it but then you know that is
exactly so if I undo this now did I see
it and that was always the main problem
not seeing where the problem is
yeah how long when you've gone to you
know saw where the problem was could be
decades well coming for the rest of life
never see it because you cannot know
what you don't see